Colonel James Morgan Papers, 1836-1859
University of Houston Libraries
Col. James Morgan Papers
1836-1859
University of Houston Libraries
1969-028
1 box, 43 items
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
University of Houston Libraries Department of Special Collections
The Col. James Morgan Papers Collection consists of personal, business, and military correspondence, as well as various indenture and tenant documents, military orders, receipts, and folk remedies. When available, hand written transcriptions are filed behind the original documents. Manuscripts date from 1836 to 1859, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1830s. The collection comprises 1 manuscript box with 43 individual items.
Biographical Note
Colonel James Morgan (1787-1866) was an early Texas settler, merchant, and land speculator. Having started out in Texas with a mercantile business, in 1835 Morgan became a real estate agent for the New Washington Association and began to purchase large tracts of land for development.
During the Texas Revolution, Morgan was the commander at Galveston Island, where he was in charge of the 1836 fortification of the island. President Sam Houston later charged him with mismanaging this project.
After the revolution, Morgan turned his interests to improving what would eventually become the Houston Ship Channel, and experimenting with cattle breeds and crop cultivation.
Scope and Contents
The Col. James Morgan Papers Collection consists of personal, business, and military correspondence, as well as various indenture and tenant documents, military orders, receipts, and folk remedies. When available, hand written transcriptions are filed behind the original documents. Manuscripts date from 1836 to 1859, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1830s. The collection comprises 1 manuscript box with 43 individual items.
The collection is divided into two series: correspondence and other materials. The correspondence series is alphabetized by the last name of the sender. If one correspondent is represented by more than one letter, that section is then additionally alphabetized by the name of the recipient. If the writer has sent more than one letter to the same person, they are filed chronologically. The other, non-correspondence series is alphabetized by main entry.
Acquisition
The majority of this collections was given to the University of Houston Libraries by Mr. and Mrs. Henry David in December of 1969.
Photocopying decisions will be made on a case-by-case basis by Special Collections staff. Patrons are responsible for obtaining permission to publish from copyright holders.
Detailed Description
- [unittitle added: see error report]
  - Correspondence: Burnett, President to Morgan, Col. James., May 22, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    (outside letter sheet only)
  - Correspondence: Cespedes, M. et. al. to Morgan, Col. James., Aug. 23, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (captured Mexican officers)
  - Correspondence: Eldredge, J.C. to Morgan, James., 1847 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Ganen, A.P. to Morgan, Col. James., Oct. 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Hockley, George W. To Morgan, Col. James., Nov. 22, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Houston, Sam to Smith, Henry., 1838 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    (outside letter sheet only, in the hand of Sam Houston)
  - Correspondence: Kaufman, David to Morgan, Col. James., Jan. 29, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Lawrence, W. To Morgan, Col. James., 20 Oct. 1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Luck, P.C. to Morgan, Col. James., Apr. 29, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Morgan, Col. James to Moore, W.R., Oct. 27, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Morgan, Col. James to Wilson, Thomas., Oct. 2, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Sawyer, F.A. to Morgan, Col. James., Sept. 1, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Stanley, Capt. Edward H. to Morgan, Col. James., Apr. 2, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Wilson, Thomas to Morgan, Col. James., Sept. 3, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Wilson, Thomas to Morgan, Col. James., Sept. 13, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clarkson, James. Indenture document., Dec. 1836 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hayden, Benedict. Indenture document., Sept. 16, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Land bill of sale to John Victery., 14 Oct. 1859 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Land deed to John Victery., 4 Apr. 1858 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Land survey for property sold to John Victery., Oct. 14, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Orders concerning a spy, Cortinez., May 24, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Receipt for bond of William M. Logan., 20 Jan. 1837 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Receipt for taxes., 31 Jan. 1842 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Receipt for oxen., May 29, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Remedy for sore-backed horses. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tenant agreement with Samuel R. Lewis, April 4, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 26)